# Naresh Kumar Devulapally

# Computer Vision, Multimodal AI

devulapa.github.io

## ABOUT ME

I am an MS Thesis candidate co-advised by <u>Dr. Junsong Yuan</u> and <u>Dr. Sreyasee Das Bhattacharjee</u> at The Visual Computing Lab in the Department of Computer Science at <u>University</u> at Buffalo, SUNY. My Research is focused on Computer Vision and Multimodal AI (Vision-Language models) with applications towards Emotion Recognition, Crowd Analytics, Transformer based Object Understanding, and Emotion Generation. My recent (first-author) works are accepted at ACM Multimedia 2023 (~25% acceptance rate) and BigMM 2023.

# **EDUCATION**

## University at Buffalo, SUNY

Buffalo, NY

MS Thesis in Computer Science (Computer Vision)

August 2022 - May 2024

# National Institute of Technology at Tiruchirappalli

Trichy, TN

B. Tech in Mechanical Engineering with minor in Computer Science

June 2016 - June 2020

## Selected Publications

- Multi-label Emotion Recognition in Conversation via Multimodal Knowledge Distillation, Naresh Kumar Devulapally\*, Sidharth Anand, Junsong Yuan, Sreyasee Das Bhattacharjee, ACM Multimedia 2023.
- AMUSE: Adaptive Multimodal Analysis for Speaker Emotion Recognition in Group Conversations, Naresh Kumar Devulapally\*, Sidharth Anand, Junsong Yuan, Sreyasee Das Bhattacharjee, Yu-Ping Chang, BigMM 2023.
- OntoQuest: Automatic Question Generation for online assessments using dynamic ontology-based strategy, Naresh Kumar Devulapally\*, A Santhanavijayan, Deepak G, 15<sup>th</sup> ICInPro 2019 (Best Paper Award).

## Experience

#### Graduate Research Assistant

August 2022 – Present

**UB** Research Foundation

Buffalo, NY

- Proposed a self-supervised Multimodal Vision Transformer Framework for Multi-Label Emotion Recognition in videos. Outperformed State-Of-The-Art models by 9% on three large public datasets.
- Proposed a Novel Adaptive Multimodal Fusion and Multi-Head Attention Framework for Speaker Emotion Recognition using video data. Outperformed SoTA by over 7% on two large public datasets.
- Created a large benchmark EmoRace dataset for Emotion Recognition with 250,000 utterances (10 times larger than the current largest benchmark), **Submitted to CVPR 2024**.
- Implemented Fully-Sharded Data Parallel pipeline to train Vision-Transformers across 8 NVIDIA A100 GPUs.
- Led a team of 4 undergrad students at UB to fine-tune Large Language Models for a large medical dataset. Used quantization techniques to improve METEOR and ROUGE score by 10%.

# Graduate Teaching Assistant

August 2022 – Present

University at Buffalo, SUNY

Buffalo, NY

- Worked as Teaching Assistant to the Pattern Recognition, Machine Learning, Data Models and Query Languages, Sports Video Analysis using Computer Vision courses.
- Created interactive lecture slides to elucidate Machine Learning and Computer Vision concepts to over 250 students every semester.
- Published online lecture notes (website format) for Computer Vision and Image Processing course.

# Lead Data Scientist

Feb 2021 – July 2022

Carbynetech Inc. Hyderabad, India

- Trained a custom Faster R-CNN model, with an ImageNet ResNeXt backbone, to detect P&ID symbols with 94% mAP. Reduced inference time by over 50% as compared to Template Matching.
- Modeled Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) for synthetic data generation & data balancing.
- Built an Azure Custom Vision AI model to detect and read labels, bar codes, and logos on export pallets with 92% mAP for a multinational engineering and technology client. Minimized per pallet inspection time by 98%.
- Increased revenue generated by the Data Science team by over 30%.

• Led end-to-end migration of 800+ GB data from 300+ production facilities worldwide for a multinational client, ensuring 99% migration efficiency.

# Machine Learning Engineer

July 2020 – January 2021

AIDesign Pvt. Ltd.

Chennai, India

• Developed Neural Networks to solve real-world fluid flow problems at a faster rate than existing commercial software with less than 5% relative error. Solved run-time & memory bottlenecks.

## PROJECTS

• Implemented text query-based image retrieval web application using OpenAI's CLIP Vision Transformer model. Performed inference optimization for retrieval from 1 Million images in under 25 seconds. Created a HuggingFace space for the project.

## **AUGMENTify** | Python, Flask, GANs, Image Processing

May 2023 – July 2023

• One-stop solution for Generative Image Augmentation. Implemented a Distributed Training pipeline for text query based Image Processing to style transfer based Generative Image Augmentation.

## Neural Network Pruning | CNNs, Inference Optimization

April 2023 - May 2023

• Optimized VGG16bn model on ImageNet dataset using iterative weight pruning techniques, achieving an accuracy of 98%, model size reduction of 26%, and an inference time speedup of 15%.

## AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Best Graduate Research Student of the Year Nominee for accepted research work in Computer Vision, Multimodal AI, Real-Time video Emotion Recognition in group conversations.
- Best Paper Award at the Fifteenth International Conference on Information Processing, ICInPro'19.
- First Honorable Mention at Agrusa L. Student Innovation Competition, 2022 for research work on Privacy Preserving Real-Time Emotion Analysis in conversations (PRIMAL).
- Second Place at Agrusa L. Student Innovation Competition, 2023 for leading research work on fine-tuning Large Language Models for Vision and Medical Applications.